because too many people drop out of the study, or funding for the research dries up, or the researchers get distracted, or they die, and nobody moves the ball further down the field. But through a combination of luck and the persistence of several generations of researchers, this study has survived. About 60 of our original 724 men are still alive, still participating in the study, most of them in their 90s. And we are now beginning to study the more than 2,000 children of these men. And I'm the fourth director of the study. Since 1938, we've tracked the lives of two groups of men. The first group started in the study when they were sophomores at Harvard College. They all finished college during World War II, and then most went off to serve in the war. And the second group that we've followed was a group of boys from Boston's poorest neighborhoods, boys who were chosen for the study specifically because they were from some of the most troubled and disadvantaged families in the Boston of the 1930s. Most lived in tenements, many without hot and cold running water. When they entered the study, all of these teenagers were interviewed. They were given medical exams. We went to their homes and we interviewed their parents. And then these teenagers grew up into adults who entered all walks of life. They became factory workers and lawyers and bricklayers and doctors, one President of the United States. Some developed alcoholism. A few developed schizophrenia. Some climbed the social ladder from the bottom all the way to the very top, and some made that journey in the opposite direction. The founders of this study would never in their wildest dreams have imagined that I would be standing here today, 75 years later, telling you that the study still continues. Every two years, our patient and dedicated research staff calls up our men and asks them if we can send them
porque muchas personas abandonan el estudio, o por falta de financiamiento, o por distracción de los investigadores, o porque mueren, y nadie continúa la investigación de campo. Pero gracias a una combinación de suerte y persistencia de varias generaciones de investigadores, este estudio sobrevivió. Unos 60 de los 724 hombres del principio siguen con vida, todavía participan en el estudio, la mayoría tiene noventa y tantos. Y ahora empezamos a estudiar los más de 2000 hijos de estos hombres. Y yo soy el cuarto director del estudio. Desde 1938, hemos rastreado las vidas de dos grupos de hombres. El primer grupo empezó el estudio cuando eran estudiantes de segundo año en la Universidad de Harvard. Todos terminaron la universidad durante la Segunda Guerra Mundial, y luego la mayoría se fue a la guerra. El segundo grupo que seguimos era un grupo de chicos de los barrios más pobres de Boston, chicos elegidos para el estudio específicamente porque provenían de las familias con más problemas y más desfavorecidas en el Boston de los años 1930. La mayoría vivía hacinada, sin agua corriente, sin agua caliente. Cuando ingresaron al estudio, se entrevistó a todos estos adolescentes. Se les realizaron exámenes médicos. Fuimos a sus hogares y entrevistamos a sus padres. Y luego estos adolescentes se hicieron adultos y cada uno hizo su vida. Algunos fueron operarios de fábrica, abogados, albañiles, médicos, uno fue presidente de EE.UU. Algunos se hicieron alcohólicos. Unos pocos sufrieron esquizofrenia. Algunos tuvieron ascenso social desde la base hasta la cumbre, y otros fueron en sentido contrario. Los fundadores de este estudio ni en sus fantasías más alocadas hubieran imaginado que yo estaría hoy aquí, 75 años después, contándoles que el estudio continúa. Cada dos años, nuestro dedicado y paciente personal de investigación llama a estos hombres y les pregunta si pueden enviarles
yet one more set of questions about their lives. Many of the inner city Boston men ask us, "Why do you keep wanting to study me? My life just isn't that interesting." The Harvard men never ask that question.
otra serie de preguntas sobre sus vidas. Muchos de los hombres de Boston nos preguntan: "¿Por qué quieren seguir estudiándome? Mi vida no es tan interesante". Los hombres de Harvard nunca hacen esa pregunta.
(Laughter) To get the clearest picture of these lives, we don't just send them questionnaires. We interview them in their living rooms. We get their medical records from their doctors. We draw their blood, we scan their brains, we talk to their children. We videotape them talking with their wives about their deepest concerns. And when, about a decade ago, we finally asked the wives if they would join us as members of the study, many of the women said, "You know, it's about time." (Laughter) So what have we learned? What are the lessons that come from the tens of thousands of pages of information that we've generated on these lives? Well, the lessons aren't about wealth or fame or working harder and harder. The clearest message that we get from this 75-year study is this: Good relationships keep us happier and healthier. Period.
(Risas) Para obtener la imagen más clara de estas vidas, no solo enviamos cuestionarios. Los entrevistamos en sus salas de estar. Conseguimos sus historias clínicas. Les extraemos sangre, escaneamos sus cerebros, hablamos con sus hijos. Registramos en video las conversaciones con sus esposas sobre sus preocupaciones. Y cuando, hace una década, finalmente les preguntamos a las esposas si querían sumarse como miembros del estudio, muchas mujeres dijeron: "Sabes, ya era hora". (Risas) ¿Qué hemos aprendido? ¿Qué lecciones surgen de las decenas de miles de páginas de información que generamos sobre estas vidas? Bueno, las lecciones no tienen que ver con riqueza, fama, ni con trabajar mucho. El mensaje más claro de estos 75 años de estudio es este: Las buenas relaciones nos hacen más felices y más saludables. Punto.
We've learned three big lessons about relationships. The first is that social connections are really good for us, and that loneliness kills. It turns out that people who are more socially connected to family, to friends, to community, are happier, they're physically healthier, and they live longer
Hemos aprendido tres cosas sobre las relaciones. La primera es que las conexiones sociales nos hacen bien, y que la soledad mata. Resulta que las personas con más vínculos sociales con la familia, los amigos, la comunidad, son más felices, más sanos y viven más
than people who are less well connected. And the experience of loneliness turns out to be toxic. People who are more isolated than they want to be from others
que las personas que tienen menos vínculos. Y experimentar soledad resulta ser tóxico. Las personas que están más aisladas de lo que quisieran de otras personas
find that they are less happy, their health declines earlier in midlife, their brain functioning declines sooner and they live shorter lives than people who are not lonely. And the sad fact is that at any given time, more than one in five Americans will report that they're lonely. And we know that you can be lonely in a crowd and you can be lonely in a marriage, so the second big lesson that we learned is that it's not just the number of friends you have, and it's not whether or not you're in a committed relationship, but it's the quality of your close relationships that matters. It turns out that living in the midst of conflict is really bad for our health. High-conflict marriages, for example, without much affection, turn out to be very bad for our health, perhaps worse than getting divorced. And living in the midst of good, warm relationships is protective. Once we had followed our men all the way into their 80s, we wanted to look back at them at midlife and to see if we could predict who was going to grow into a happy, healthy octogenarian and who wasn't. And when we gathered together everything we knew about them at age 50, it wasn't their middle age cholesterol levels that predicted how they were going to grow old. It was how satisfied they were in their relationships. The people who were the most satisfied in their relationships at age 50 were the healthiest at age 80. And good, close relationships seem to buffer us from some of the slings and arrows of getting old. Our most happily partnered men and women reported, in their 80s, that on the days when they had more physical pain, their mood stayed just as happy. But the people who were in unhappy relationships, on the days when they reported more physical pain, it was magnified by more emotional pain. And the third big lesson that we learned about relationships and our health is that good relationships don't just protect our bodies, they protect our brains. It turns out that being in a securely attached relationship to another person in your 80s is protective, that the people who are in relationships where they really feel they can count on the other person in times of need, those people's memories stay sharper longer. And the people in relationships where they feel they really can't count on the other one, those are the people who experience earlier memory decline. And those good relationships, they don't have to be smooth all the time.
encuentran que son menos felices, son más susceptibles a recaídas de salud en la mediana edad, sus funciones cerebrales decaen más precipitadamente y viven menos que las personas que no están solas. Y lo triste es que, en cualquier momento, más de 1 de cada 5 estadounidenses informarán estar solos. Y sabemos que podemos estar solos en la multitud y podemos estar solos en un matrimonio, por eso la segunda gran lección que aprendimos es que no tiene que ver con la cantidad de amigos que tenemos, tampoco tiene que ver con que estemos en una relación, lo que importa es la calidad de las relaciones más cercanas. Resulta que vivir en medio del conflicto es muy malo para la salud. Los matrimonios muy conflictivos, por ejemplo, sin mucho afecto, resultan ser muy malos para la salud, quizá peores que el divorcio. Y vivir en medio de relaciones buenas y cálidas da protección. Cuando nuestros hombres llegaron a sus ochenta y tantos, quisimos analizar cómo fue su mediana edad para ver si podíamos predecir quién se convertiría en un octogenario feliz y saludable y quién no. Y cuando recolectamos todo lo que sabíamos de ellos a sus 50 años, no fueron los niveles de colesterol de la mediana edad los que predijeron cómo envejecerían. Fue el grado de satisfacción que tenían en sus relaciones. Las personas más satisfechas en sus relaciones a los 50 años fueron las más saludables a los 80 años. Y bueno, las relaciones cercanas parecen amortiguar algunos de los achaques de envejecer. Nuestras hombres y mujeres que están en parejas felices informaron, a sus ochenta y tantos, que cuando sentían más dolor físico, seguían de buen humor. Pero las personas que estaban en relaciones no felices, los días que informaban tener más dolor físico, este se magnificaba por el dolor emocional. Y la tercera gran lección que aprendimos sobre las relaciones y la salud es que las buenas relaciones no solo protegen el cuerpo, protegen el cerebro. Resulta que estar en una relación de apego seguro con otra persona a los 80 y tantos da protección, las personas que están en relaciones en las que sienten que pueden contar con la otra persona si lo necesitan, los recuerdos de esas personas permanecen más nítidos más tiempo. Y las personas en relaciones en que sienten que no pueden contar con la otra persona, son personas que pierden antes la memoria. Pero las buenas relaciones pueden no ser armoniosas todo el tiempo.
Some of our octogenarian couples could bicker with each other day in and day out, but as long as they felt that they could really count on the other when the going got tough, those arguments didn't take a toll on their memories. So this message, that good, close relationships are good for our health and well-being, this is wisdom that's as old as the hills. Why is this so hard to get and so easy to ignore? Well, we're human. What we'd really like is a quick fix, something we can get that'll make our lives good and keep them that way. Relationships are messy and they're complicated and the hard work of tending to family and friends, it's not sexy or glamorous. It's also lifelong. It never ends. The people in our 75-year study who were the happiest in retirement were the people who had actively worked to replace workmates with new playmates. Just like the millennials in that recent survey, many of our men when they were starting out as young adults really believed that fame and wealth and high achievement were what they needed to go after to have a good life. But over and over, over these 75 years, our study has shown that the people who fared the best were the people who leaned in to relationships,
Algunas de nuestras parejas octogenarias podían pelearse a veces pero en tanto sintieran que podían contar con el otro cuando la cosa se ponía difícil, esas pelean no quedaban en sus recuerdos. Pero este mensaje, de que las relaciones buenas y estrechas son buenas para la salud y el bienestar, esta sabiduría es vieja como el tiempo. ¿Por qué es tan difícil de entender y tan fácil de ignorar? Bueno, somos humanos. Nos gustaría una solución rápida, algo que nos mejore la vida y que sea permanente. Las relaciones son un lío, son complicadas, y cuidar a la familia y a los amigos no es atractivo ni glamuroso. Dura toda la vida. Nunca termina. En el estudio, las personas de 75 años más felices al jubilarse fueron las que activamente reemplazaron compañeros de trabajo por nuevos compañeros de juego. Como los encuestados de la generación del milenio, muchos de nuestros hombres cuando eran adultos jóvenes creían que la fama, la riqueza y lograr grandes cosas era lo que necesitaban para tener una vida buena. Pero con el tiempo, en estos 75 años, nuestro estudio ha demostrado que les fue mejor a las personas que se inclinaron por las relaciones,
with family, with friends, with community. So what about you? Let's say you're 25, or you're 40, or you're 60. What might leaning in to relationships even look like? Well, the possibilities are practically endless. It might be something as simple as replacing screen time with people time or livening up a stale relationship by doing something new together, long walks or date nights, or reaching out to that family member who you haven't spoken to in years, because those all-too-common family feuds take a terrible toll on the people who hold the grudges.
con la familia, con los amigos, con la comunidad. ¿Qué hay de ti? Digamos que tienes 25, o 40, o 60. ¿Qué implica entregarse a las relaciones? Bueno, las posibilidades son casi ilimitadas. Podría ser tan simple como pasar más tiempo con personas que con pantallas o amenizar una relación rancia haciendo algo nuevo juntos, caminatas largas o citas nocturnas, o acercarse a ese familiar que no hemos visto en años, porque esas disputas familiares tan comunes dejan una pérdida terrible en las personas que guardan rencores.
I'd like to close with a quote from Mark Twain. More than a century ago, he was looking back on his life, and he wrote this: "There isn't time, so brief is life, for bickerings, apologies, heartburnings, callings to account. There is only time for loving, and but an instant, so to speak, for that." The good life is built with good relationships. Thank you. (Applause)
Me gustaría cerrar con una cita de Mark Twain. Hace más de un siglo, él estaba analizando su vida, y escribió esto: "No hay tiempo, muy breve es la vida para disputas, disculpas, animosidades, pedidos de cuenta. Solo hay tiempo para amar, y solo un instante, por así decirlo, para eso". La buena vida se construye con buenas relaciones. Gracias. (Aplausos)